Finding Aid for John Monteith papers, 1797-1885 [microform]
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John Monteith papers [microform] 1797-1885
Monteith, John, 1788-1868.
4 microfilm rolls
852041 mf286c—mf289c
Presbyterian minister in Elyria, Ohio, Detroit and Blissfield, Michigan; professor at Hamilton College and first president of University of Michigan; correspondence, diaries, sermons, speeches, and papers of other family members.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection of original materials was the gift of Caroline Monteith (donor no. 347 ) and Mrs. George Stevens (donor no. 1179 ). Other materials were transferred from the library of the University of Michigan.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The microfilm collection is open to research. Access to the original materials is restricted for preservation purposes.
The originals of the Montieth papers are located at the Bentley Historical Library.
John Monteith was born in Gettysburg, Pennsylvania, on August 5, 1788. He graduated in 1813 from Jefferson College (name later changed to Washington and Jefferson). He continued his studies at Princeton Theological Seminary, graduating from there in 1816. Responding to a call to preach the gospel to the Protestant citizens of Detroit, Monteith moved to the Michigan Territory soon after graduation. In 1817, Monteith and the Reverend Father Gabriel Richard, Catholic Bishop of Michigan, along with other individuals began in Detroit the school which would become the University of Michigan. The name given for their institution was the Catholepistemiad or University of Michigania. Monteith served as first president with Father Gabriel Richard as vice president. During the five years that Monteith spent in Detroit, he also founded the First Protestant Society of Detroit (which became First Presbyterian Church); he also organized Michigan's oldest Presbyterian Church in Monroe; and he helped organize the Detroit library society. In 1821 Monteith went to Hamilton College in Clinton, New York, where he had been appointed to the chair of ancient languages. He later taught at Cambridge, New York and Germantown, Pennsylvania. He next moved on to Elyria, Ohio. In 1845, he was pastor of the Presbyterian Church in Blissfield, Michigan. He stayed here for ten years, then returned to Elyria, where he died on May 27, 1868.
The John Monteith microfilm collection consists of correspondence, diaries, sermons, and papers of other family members. The originals of these materials are also available at the library; to best preserve the originals, access is limited to the microfilm copies.
The correspondence includes letters from Monteith to members of his family and other discussing current events, his work, travel, places visited, temperance reform, slavery, and bank failures. There are also letters of Monteith's wife Abigail, his daughter Sarah, his sons George, John Jr., Charles, and Edwin, and scattered letters from other relatives and friends. George's letters cover his service as an officer in the Fourth Michigan Infantry during the Civil War. Besides the letters there are diaries kept by Monteith (1815-1838), notes on his library, sermons and a volume of sermon outlines, speeches, notes on class lectures and other subjects, personal account books, a notebook (1820) containing Chippewa-English vocabulary, student notes (1797-1798) taken by Alexander Monteith at Dickinson College. Of special interest is the annual report, Nov. 1818, of John Monteith to governor and judges of Michigan Territory concerning the University of Michigania. In addition, there is a manuscript play written by John Monteith Jr. entitled, "The Raging Firelands."
Subjects:
Banks and banking--Michigan.; Blissfield (Mich.); Catholepistemiad (Detroit, Mich.); Ojibwa Indians--Michigan.; Detroit (Mich.); Dickinson College.; Elyria (Ohio); Hamilton College (Clinton, N.Y.); Indians of North America--Michigan.; Monteith, John, 1788-1868.; Presbyterian Church--Michigan--Detroit.; Antislavery movements--United States.; Temperance--United States.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 4th (1861-1864); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; University of Michigan. President.; Women--Michigan--Detroit.; Mexican War, 1846-1848.; Spouses of clergy--Michigan--Detroit.; Clergy--Michigan--Detroit.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
African American women--War.; Military camps.; Military officers.; Monteith, John, 1788-1868.; Monteith family.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Contributors:
Monteith, Abigail Harris, b. 1801.; Monteith, Alexander.; Monteith, Charles.; Monteith, Edward H.; Monteith, Edwin Harris.; Monteith, George, b. 1840.; Monteith, John, 1833-1918.; Monteith, Sarah S.
Genre Terms:
Account books.; Diaries.; Sermons.; Daguerreotypes.; Photographs.; Tintypes.
- Correspondence
  - 1817-1851 (Reel 1)
  - 1852-1853 (Reel 1)
  - 1854-1855 (Reel 1)
  - 1856-1857 (Reel 1)
  - 1858-1859 (Reel 1)
  - 1860-1861 (Reel 1)
  - 1862-1885 (Reel 1)
- Diaries
  - 1808-1819 (original and copy) (Reel 1)
  - 1819-1821 (original and copy) (Reel 1)
  - Fragments of diaries (Reel 2)
    - 1815, 1818-1819 (Reel 2)
    - 1822-1838 (Reel 2)
- Parish Memorandum of Admissions
  - Baptisms 1817-1820 (Reel 2)
  - Marriages 1818-1827 (Reel 2)
- Sermons
  - 1815-1816 (Reel 2)
  - 1816 (Reel 2)
  - 1817 (Reel 2)
  - 1818-1822 (Reel 2)
  - 1831 (Reel 2)
  - 1845-1847 (Reel 2)
  - 1847-1848 (Reel 2)
  - 1848-1849 (Reel 2)
  - 1850 (Reel 2)
  - 1850-1851 (Reel 2)
  - 1851 (Reel 3)
  - 1852 (Reel 3)
  - 1853 (Reel 3)
  - 1854-1858 (Reel 3)
- Other papers
  - Addresses (Reel 3)
  - Miscellaneous notes, including First Annual Report of the University of Michigania November 16, 1818 and John Monteith's commission to the U.S. Christian Commission, May 17, 1864 (Reel 3)
  - Bible notebook (Reel 3)
  - Copies of documents containing Monteith signature (Reel 3)
  - Latin exercises (Reel 3)
  - Vocabulary of Chippewa language (Reel 3)
  - Catalog of books in Monteith's library (Reel 3)
  - Account books
    - 1813-1844 (Reel 3)
    - 1848-1853 (Reel 3)
  - Obituary notice and will of John Monteith (Reel 3)
  - Works about John Monteith (Reel 3)
  - School notebooks of Alexander Monteith
    - 1797 (Reel 3)
    - 1798 (Reel 3)
  - Biography of Abigail Monteith written by her son, Edwin H. Monteith (Reel 3)
    (donor no. 3926)
- "The Raging Firelands"
  - Papers relating to "The Raging Firelands" by John Monteith, Jr.; including "Reminiscences of Elyria, Ohio" by Mrs. Mary Beebe Hall 1900 (Reel 4)
  - Manuscript, "The Raging Firelands"
    - Chapters 1-5 (Reel 4)
    - Chapters 6-10 (Reel 4)
    - Chapters 11-15 (Reel 4)
    - Chapters 16-20 (Reel 4)
    - Chapters 21-25 (Reel 4)
    - Chapters 26-30 (Reel 4)
    - Chapters 31-35 (Reel 4)
    - Chapters 36-40 (Reel 4)
    - Chapters 41-45 (Reel 4)
  - Typescript, "The Raging Firelands"
    - Chapters 1-10 (Reel 4)
    - Chapters 11-20 (Reel 4)
    - Chapters 21-30 (Reel 4)
    - Chapters 31-40 (Reel 4)
    - Chapters 41-45 (Reel 4)
- Photographs
  - Portraits of Monteith and members of the Monteith family (Reel 4)
  - Photograph, taken by Matthew Brady, of the Civil War staff of General Fitz John Porter, showing George Monteith (Reel 4)